Guide to the Godfrey Barnsley Papers, 1824-1873, bulk 1840-1861 RL.10099
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Godfrey Barnsley papers
1824-1873
bulk
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Barnsley, Godfrey
RL.10099
3 Linear Feet (6 boxes; 3,668 items)
Godfrey Barnsley (1805-1873), of Savannah, Ga., was an agent for general import and export brokers of Liverpool, England.
Collection includes letters to Barnsley from his children, correspondence among his children, accounts with physicians, accounts for building expenses of Barnsley's estate, "Woodlands," near Kingston, Ga., and records of sales and imports of cotton. Letters from children concern school life while his sons attended a New England preparatory school and daughters were at the Montpelier Female Institute, near Macon, Ga. There are also letters from son Harold describing his voyage around Cape Horn and travels to the North, and in China, where he eventually settled. Civil War material includes letters from Godfrey's sons and information on the depredations suffered by the family. Beginning in 1867 there are letters from two Barnsley sons who emigrated to South America: George, a physician, and Lucien, who at different times operated a rice mill, apothecary's shop, brick manufactory, and Brazilian gold mine. Their letters describe the inhabitants, the countryside, and political, social, and economic conditions in Brazil. Throughout much of the collection there are references to spiritualism, seances, and mediums.
Biographical Note
Godfrey Barnsley (1805-1873), of Savannah, Ga., was an agent for general import and export brokers of Liverpool, England.
Collection Overview
Collection contains letters to Godfrey Barnsley (1805-1872), Savannah agent for general import and export brokers of Liverpool, England, from his children; correspondence among the children; detailed lists comprised of accounts with physicians, invoices, prices of building materials for "Woodlands" (Barnsley's estate), records of sales and imports of cotton, bills, and receipts.
There are letters from three of the Barnsley sons who attended the preparatory school of Charles Green at Jamaica Plain, Massachusetts; and letters from Barnsley's three daughters at Montpelier Female Institute, near Macon, Georgia. Much of the material concerns Harold Barnsley, who traveled over New England and other northern sections of the United States, in China, and on the seas; references to the Civil War, in which several of the sons served, and to depredations suffered by the family.
Beginning in 1867 there are several letters from two of Barnsley's sons, George, a physician, and Lucien, both of whom went to South America with an emigrant group under the leadership of one McMullen. They shortly severed connections with this group, however. George followed his profession, while Lucien engaged in a number of enterprises, operating in turn a rice mill, apothecary's shop, brick manufactory, and gold mine. Most of this work was at Iguape, Sao Paulo Province, and near Rio de Janeiro, Brazil. The letters contain descriptions of the natives, the countryside, and political, social and economic conditions of the country.
The collection also contains a ledger, 1828-1844.
Throughout much of the papers there are references to spiritualism, seances, and mediums.
Provenance
The Godfrey Barnsley Papers were acquired by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library in 1933-1934, 1941, 1951, and 1953.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Savannah (Ga.) -- History; Georgia -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Brazil -- Description and travel; Voyages and travels; Family life; Export trading companies -- Southern States; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Spiritualism -- Southern States; Education -- Southern States; Barnsley, Harold; Montpelier Female Academy (Macon, Ga.); Barnsley, Lucien; Barnsley, Godfrey
- Godfrey Barnsley Papers, 1805-1893; 1
  - Papers, 1824-1846 (Box 1)
  - Papers, 1847-1852 (Box 2)
  - Papers, 1853-1856 August (Box 3)
  - Papers, 1856 Sept.-1859 Dec. (Box 4)
  - Papers, 1860 Jan.-1868 Dec. (Box 5)
  - Papers, 1869-1873 (Box 6)
  - Letter copy book, 1866 Oct.-1867 Aug. (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous letters (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous clippings (Box 6)
  - Journal, 1828-1844 (Volume F:293)